Chapter 56. Of the less erroneous pictures of whales and the true pictures of whailing scenes.
In connection with the monstrous pictures of whales, I am strongly
tempted here to enter upon those still more monstrous stories of them which are
to be found in certain books both ancient and modern, especially in Ply,
Purchase, Hackloot, Harris, Kovier, etc.
But I pass that matter by.
I know of only four published outlines of the great sperm whale. Colnuts,
Huggin's Frederick Kouier, and Beiels.
In the previous chapter, Colnet and Kovier have been referred to. Huggin's
is far better than theirs, but by great odds, Beiels is the best. All Beal's
drawings of this whale are good, excepting the middle figure in the
picture of three whales in various attitudes, capping his second chapter.
His frontest piece, Boats Attacking Sperm Whales, though no doubt calculated
to excite the civil skepticism of some parlor men, is admirably correct and
lifelike in its general effect. Some of these sperm whale drawings in J Ross
Brown are pretty correct in contour, but they are wretchedly engraved. This is
not his fault, though.
of the right whale. The best outline pictures are in Scoresby, but they are
drawn on too small a scale to convey a desirable impression. He has but one
picture of whailing scenes, and this is a sad deficiency, because it is by such
pictures only, when at all well done, that you can derive anything like a
truthful idea of the living whale, as seen by his living hunters.
But taken for all in all, by far the finest, though in some details not the
most correct, presentations of whales and whailing scenes to be anywhere found
are two large French engravings well executed and taken from paintings by one
garnery respectively. They represent attacks on the sperm and right whale. In
the first engraving, a noble sperm whale is depicted in full majesty of might,
just risen beneath the boat from the profoundities of the ocean, and bearing
high in the air upon his back the terrific wreck of the sto planks. The
prow of the boat is partially unbroken, and is drawn just balancing upon the
monster's spine. And standing in that prow, for that one single incomputable
flash of time, you behold an orsman half shrouded by the incensed boiling spout
of the whale, and in the act of leaping as if from a precipice. The action of
the whole thing is wonderfully good and true. The half emptied line tub floats
on the whiten sea. The wooden poles of the spilled harpoons obliquely bob in
it. The heads of the swimming crew are scattered about the whale in contrasting
expressions of a fright. While in the black stormy distance, the ship is
bearing down upon the scene. Serious fault might be found with the anatomical
details of this whale, but let that pass, since for the life of me I could
not draw so good of one.
In the second engraving, the boat is in the act of drawing alongside the
barnacled flank of a large running right whale that rolls his black weedy bulk in
the sea like some mossy rock slide from the Patagonian cliffs. His jets are
erect, full and black like soot, so that from so abounding a smoke in the
chimney, you would think that there must be a brave supper cooking in the great
boughels below. Sea fowls are pecking at the small crabs, shellfish, and other
sea candies and macaroni, which the right whale sometimes carries on his
pestilent back. And all the while the thick-lipped Leviathan is rushing
through the deep, leaving tons of tumultuous white Kurds in his wake, and
causing the slight boat to rock in the swells like a skiff caught nigh the
paddle wheels of an ocean steamer.
Thus the foreground is all raging commotion, but behind in admirable
artistic contrast is the glassy level of a sea be calmed, the drooping
unstarchched sails of the powerless ship, and the inert mass of a dead
whale, a conquered fortress, with the flag of capture lazily hanging from the
whale pole inserted into his spout hole.
Who Garnery, the painter, is or was, I know not. But my life for it, he was
either practically conversant with his subject, or else marvelously tutored by
some experienced whaleman. The French are the lads for painting action. Go and
gaze upon all the paintings of Europe, and where will you find such a gallery
of living and breathing commotion on canvas, as in that triumphal hall at
Versailles, where the beholder fights his way pelmel through the consecutive
great battles of France, where every sword seems a flash of the northern
lights, and the successive armed kings and emperors dash by like a charge of
crowned centaurs, not wholly unworthy of a place in that gallery are these sea
battle pieces of garnnery.
The natural aptitude of the French for seizing the pictures of things seems to
be peculiarly evinced in what paintings and engravings they have of their
whaling scenes. With not onetenth of England's experience in the fishery, and
not the thousandth part of that of the Americans, they have nevertheless
furnished both nations with the only finished sketches at all capable of
conveying the real spirit of the whale hunt. For the most part, the English and
American whale draftsmen seem entirely content with presenting the mechanical
outline of things such as the vacant profile of the whale, which so far as
pictures of effect is concerned, is about tantamount to sketching the
profile of a pyramid. Even Scoresby, the justly renowned right whaleman, after
giving us a stiff full length of the Greenland whale and three or four
delicate miniatures of narwhales and porpuses, treats us to a series of
classical engravings of boat hooks, chopping knives, and grapels, and with
the microscopic diligence of a Luenhawk, submits to the inspection of a shivering
world 96 faximiles of magnified Arctic thick snow crystals. I mean, no
disparagement to the excellent Voyager, I honor him for a veteran, but in so
important a matter, it was certainly an oversight not to have procured for every
crystal a sworn affidavit taken before a Greenland justice of the peace.
In addition to those fine engravings from Garnery, there are two other French
engravings worthy of note by someone who subscribes himself H. Duran. One of
them, though not precisely adapted to our present purpose, nevertheless
deserves mention on other accounts. It is a quiet noon scene among the aisles
of the Pacific. A French whaler anchored inshore in a calm and lazily taking
water on board, the loosened sails of the ship, and the long leaves of the
palms in the background, both drooping together in the breezeless air. The
effect is very fine when considered with reference to its presenting the hearty
fishermen under one of their few aspects of oriental repose. The other engraving
is quite a different affair. The ship ho too on the open seas and in the very
heart of the Leviathanic life with a right whale alongside the vessel in the
act of cutting in ho over to the monster as if to a quay and a boat hurriedly
pushing off from this scene of activity is about giving chase to whales in the
distance. The harpoons and lances lie leveled for use. Three oresmen are just
setting the mast in its hole, while from a sudden roll of the sea, the little
craft stands half erect out of the water like a rearing horse. From the ship the
smoke of the torments of the boiling whale is going up like the smoke over a
village of smithies, and to windward a black cloud rising up with earnest of
squalls and rains, seems to quicken the activity of the excited seaman.